[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio i
am your host prajesh ammanath and today
my guest is rob hirschfeldt
rob is ceo and co-founder of raken
leaders in physical and hybrid devops
software he has been in the cloud and
infrastructure space for nearly 15 years
from working with early esx betas to
serving four terms on the openstack
foundation board
and becoming an executive at dell
as a co-founder of the digital rebar
project rob is creating a new generation
of devops orchestration to leverage the
containers and service oriented ops he
is trained as an industrial engineer and
is passionate about applying lean and
agile processes to software delivery rob
welcome to software engineering radio
projection it's a pleasure to be here
i'm really looking forward to the
conversation
excellent we will be talking about
infrastructure as code with a specific
focus on bare metal we have covered
infrastructure as code previously in
episode 268 405 and 482 i would like to
start a session by doing a quick
refresher of the basics
infrastructure as code infrastructure as
a service and bare metal as a service
how are these different
oh boy that's a great question to start
with infrastructure's code to me is is
very different than infrastructure as a
service and bare metal as a service
infrastructure as code is this idea of
of being able to build automation
because that's what we call software
that runs and sets up infrastructure but
do it with code-like principles so
modularity reuse collaboration get you
know having a ci cd pipeline those are
all development processes that need to
be brought into
our infrastructure processes our
operations teams and infrastructure as
code to me
talks about doing exactly that that
change in mindset that it comes to we
have a couple of tools that are called
infrastructure as code tools terraform
or ansible
come to mind most readily but those are
really tools that handle only a part of
the process it would be like looking at
a single python module and hey i can i
can serve up a web but i can't connect
to a database
infrastructure as code really talks
about the process by which we're
developing maintaining and sustaining
that automation
infrastructure is a service
you know a lot of people equate that
with a vm hosting or a cloud service it
really is very simply
having a infrastructure that is api
driven so
if you have compute networking storage
components that are able to be
addressed through an api that would be
infrastructure as a service to me bare
metal as a service is a subclass of that
where you are talking about the physical
layer of the infrastructure and enabling
that to have an api in front of it that
handles all the pieces it's much more
complex than what people are used to for
infrastructure as a service because
there's a lot of raid and bios and pixie
booting there's additional complexities
in that that are worth exploring and i'm
assuming we'll get to
absolutely you also touched on tooling
which is a topic that we'll come to
later in the talk but first i want to
just make sure that we have covered the
basics and done a deep dive on bare
metal
what specific use cases or workloads are
most suitable for a bare metal server
any examples you can recollect where
clients benefited by using badminton
at the end of the day every workload
runs on bare metal we'd love to talk
about things like serverless or cloud
those services don't exist without bare
metal somewhere deep underneath the
surface so at some point every service
can be run on bare metal there are
prices to be paid for running things
directly on bare metal meaning that you
have to manage that infrastructure and
so if you're running you know we get a
lot of people who are interested in say
running a kubernetes stack which is a
containerized orchestration system
directly on bare metal to eliminate the
virtualization layer so let me step back
a second typically on bare metal
you run systems that either
abstract the bare metal away so you
don't have to deal with management so
that would be a virtualized system like
vmware or xan or kpm and that's what
most of the clouds do when they offer
you a server they're actually using a
layer like that above the bare metal and
offering that so that's would be
infrastructure as a services typical
system so virtualization is always going
to run on a bare metal substrate and
there are some places where you want a
lot of performance like a high
performance workload or a data analytics
system
those also typically run on bare metal
because you don't want to have any
additional overhead on the system or the
workload that you're doing just requires
all the capacity of the system so you
don't need to virtualize it even so some
people still virtualize because it just
makes it easier to manage
systems or we've gotten so good at
managing bare metal now that the benefit
of adding virtualization just to improve
management is really dropping to zero
and then there is another class of bare
metal that people are starting to care
about which is edge infrastructure so in
an edge site you're typically deploying
very small footprint devices and it
doesn't make sense to virtualize them or
you don't want to add the complexity of
virtualizing them and so
we do see places where people are
talking about bare metal and bare metal
automation because they just don't have
the resources on the systems they're
deploying to add a virtualization layer
so there's there's broad range from that
perspective when would you not use
badminton there are times when you might
decide that you don't want to manage the
bare metal so like i said before you're
always using bare metal somewhere but in
a lot of cases people don't want to deal
with
the additional complexity for using bare
metal so in a lot of cases you would
argue the other way around when should i
use bare metal instead of not but the
reasons that you don't are being able to
deliver infrastructure in a virtualized
package really really simplifies how you
set up the systems so if you're putting
a virtualization on top of that then
the person using the infrastructure
doesn't have to worry about
setting the rate of bios they don't have
to worry about the security on
out-of-band management they don't have
to worry about networking because you
can control the networking in a virtual
machine a lot more it really just
provides you a much more controlled
environment so you want to use these
virtualized layers on top of bare metal
to remove complexity from
people in your organization provide that
abstraction that's typically what we see
it's a really good use for it there's
another case where your servers just
have a lot more capacity than you need
and so the other benefit of
virtualizing on top of bare metal is
that you can actually over subscribe the
systems and you can have 10 20 100
servers that are dedicated to different
uses on a piece of bare metal and serve
a lot more customers with that one piece
of equipment that is another place where
the ability to share or partition work
really is a value to a lot of companies
what is the difference between the two
offerings first is a bare metal with a
hypervisor and second is a dedicated
host where the hypervisor is managed by
the cloud provider
we see
that if you are
running the whole thing yourself even if
you virtualized it there are some really
significant benefits to
being able to balance the workload
that's on that system to know that
you're not with what they call noisy
neighbors in a cloud provider situation
where you're just getting a virtual
machine without knowing what's going on
underneath
you could get virtual machines that are
on systems that are very busy that have
somebody who's really taxing the
resources on that system and starving
your virtual machine and you don't have
any way to know that you could also be
in a situation where you've been
assigned a slower or an old system
something with slower memory so the
performance of your virtual machine
could suffer
based on circumstances are completely
outside of your control and so there's a
pretty significant benefit if you're
worried about performance or you're
worried about consistency
in the results to actually
have full control of the stack and it's
can be cheaper cloud services are
expensive services they charge premiums
for what they do and so
our customers definitely find that if
they buy the hardware they buy the
virtualization layer they can save a
significant amount of money over the
course of a year
by basically having full control and
ownership of that stack rather than
renting a vm on a per month or per
minute basis
thank you we are going to dig a bit
deeper into bare metal infrastructure as
a service so moving on to bare metal
provisioning
what makes bare metal provisioning
difficult
there's a lot of things that make bare
metal a challenge i'm going to try and
break them into a couple of pieces one
of them is just the fact that the
servers themselves have a lot of moving
parts in them
so
when you are managing a server
it has multiple network interfaces
it has multiple storage devices usually
has some type of raid controller
it has firmware for the device it
actually has firmware for the ram it has
firmware for the drives it has firmware
for the out-of-band management it has
its own out-of-band management
controller which means that there's a
separate interface for the systems that
you use to set the firmware or control
its power and things like that and so
all of those pieces together
translate into
you know you you can't
ignore
that aspect of the system so you
actually have to build the systems to
match how they're configured and what
their capabilities are and setting all
that stuff up
is a much more
now we've automated it but it requires a
lot more
information a lot more skills a lot more
knowledge and so bare metal itself
becomes more challenging and even if you
took something as simple as a raspberry
pi
it has those same limitations and you
have to understand how to deal with them
and set up the operating system to match
into that environment so that's a piece
of the puzzle the other thing about it
is
within that machine you also have
external needs for controlling the
machine so
we talk about something called pixi a
lot pxe
it's a pre-execution environment that is
actually running on the network
interface cards of the server that
handles that initial boot provision
process so
in order to
install software on a physical machine
you have to have a way to have that
machine boot
talk to the network which means talking
to your dhcp server your dhcp server has
to understand how to answer the request
for this pixie provisioning has to send
in an infrastructure you actually then
send a series of os's there's a boot
sequence so for what we do with digital
rebar there's four distinct boot
provision cycles that go into doing that
process and so you're literally sending
a bootloader and then another bootloader
and another bootloader until you get up
to one to you get up to installing an
operating system and all of that
requires infrastructure and then the
pixie process has actually been around
for over two decades it's it's well
established but there's new processes
that are coming when people use uefi the
new firmware that's coming out
or this that's embedded in servers now
and that actually has a slightly
different process that skips some boot
loader components but has different
configuration requirements if i'm not
making people's head spin yet
that you should be either you're used to
doing sort of this the sequential boot
process
and what i'm saying makes sense or
you're thinking all right i'm never
gonna want to do that and that's exactly
why people install virtualization
but there's a huge but here it is all
now it's pretty well figured out ground
and the need to be like you know rack in
and understand how the boot provision
process works and things like that has
really diminished so you know nowadays
you can stand up simple service that
will automate that full process for you
manage the bios rate and firmware and do
all that configuration you have to be
aware that it's happening on your behalf
but you don't really have to understand
the nuances of
multi-stage pixie boot provisioning
process
so if i'm able to summarize it the way i
understood it the challenges are around
the differences in the bare metal
servers itself as well as the
different ways of controlling the boot
process
and the configuration of the servers is
that a right summary
that is right that is exactly what makes
it challenging i would actually add
there's one more thing here that is
also hard
installing operating systems themselves
also have the actual
operating system process of mapping onto
that infrastructure
is also challenging from that
perspective so dif each operating system
has different ways that it adapts to the
infrastructure that is being installed
on you know debian ubuntu has a precede
process
red hat centos error things have
something called a kickstart process
that it does all this configuration
windows has its own specific thing
and for a lot of our customers they
don't they choose not to do any of that
and they'll build a pre-baked image and
they'll write that image directly to
disk
and skip a lot of that configuration
process but those are another place
where people often stumble
in building bare metal infrastructure
because they have to figure out all of
those pieces even with vms you have to
figure it out but a lot of it's sort of
baked in for vms
you also mentioned yuffie is that a
newer standard to pixel and what are the
advantages it offers
so ufe or uefi bios is actually what is
embedded in all of the computers
motherboards to run the operating
systems and this has been around for
about 10 years now but it's only slowly
coming in as the standard
what people would be used to the
alternative for for ufe is legacy bios
which is what used to run servers if you
have a desktop most desktops now run
uefi bios by default and exclusively
in this data center world uefi bios
actually changed some ways that that
systems are addressed and still trips
people up in security problems or
actually just a whole bunch of security
issues announced with ufi bios have to
be patched and so
people who had existing data centers
often put servers back in legacy mode
ua5 bios also has a different pixie
process slightly different pixie process
and they can skip the legacy pixie and
switch into ipixi much more quickly or
even skip into a higher level bootloader
beyond that and it's worth noting
for all that we're talking this is very
server heavy network switches have
similar challenges and similar processes
and so bootstrapping a switching
infrastructure is also a bare metal
provisioning and install process that
requires another stack of automation and
logic
what kind of effort and lead time do you
need to add more compute or ram or
storage to a bare metal setup
you know interestingly a lot of the
times that we work in data centers
people don't
modify existing servers as much as they
modify the footprint they buy for new
servers
it is much less common in my experience
for somebody to
say add a couple of sticks of ram or new
drives into a system they might replace
failing ones but typically they don't
go in and modify them that said if you
were doing that what you would look at
would be
like adding adding additional ram
doesn't necessarily cause a lot of
overhead in the system rebooting this
you know and you can identify the new
ram adding drives
to a system can be very disruptive to
the system or even network cards also
can be disruptive because
those devices can change the enumeration
of the systems that you have in place
and so you know we talked about this
precede and kickstart process and
configuring all these pieces when all
those are connected into a bare metal
server they have a bus order they're
actually connected and identified and
they have unique identifiers and they
also have a sequence depending on how
the operating system sees them
it can actually change the way they're
listed to the operating system and this
is a good example for going from legacy
bios to ua5 ios i mentioned that that
changes things it changes in some cases
the way the drives are enumerated in a
system so you might have a system that's
working great in legacy mode
switch the bios to uv mode and then the
drive enumeration is different
and the operating system no longer works
or drives that were attached are no
longer attached in the places you
expected them to be and that's
incredibly disruptive so we see that
change quite a bit as companies no
longer support legacy bios the
enterprises are being having forced
migrations to uefi by us and flipping
that switch actually makes it look like
they got new drives or added drives or
rewired their drive infrastructure and
that's incredibly disruptive from that
perspective it's one of the reasons why
people typically don't
modify systems in place they typically
buy whole new systems and treat them as
a converged unit
so if i understood you correctly what
you're saying is that the sequencing
of the drivers itself could change
which could have an impact in terms of
the hardware
running
properly the way the operating system
addresses that hardware that's exactly
right it can also do things like change
the boot order of the network interfaces
and depending on how you've mapped your
network interfaces that means that the
mac address that you've registered for a
server
that can confuse the dhcp server that's
then running the ip systems underneath
your servers and so those types of
sequence changes can cause disruptions
too
the way
infrastructure gets built and this is
true for cloud as much as bare metal the
order of operations the sequence of
things you know identifiers and
addresses
get coded into systems and it can be
very difficult to unwind those types of
problems we've had experiences where
people made what they thought would be a
very small change in a server
configuration in the bios
or patched bios which changed the order
that their network interfaces came
online and so a different nick was the
first one and came up first and then
that tried to pixie boot the server but
it's very down in the weeds story but it
illustrates the point
when that nick came up first the dhcp
server thought it was a new server
and told it to re-image the server which
was not well received by the operating
team and so those types of resiliency
building that type of resilience into
the system is actually a big part of
what we've done over time
actually in that specific case we built
a whole fingerprinting system into
digital rebar so that when servers come
up we can actually not rely on whether
the mac addresses which mac address is
asked for the image but we can
fingerprint the systems and
look at serial numbers baked deep into
the hardware to identify and map in
which server is which so that we don't
get faked out if somebody makes a change
like that which
happens more than you you might expect
and when it does
rewriting somebody's discs
never is a popular thing unless they
wanted it done
agreed it does sound very disruptive
yeah there's a lot of defensive
technology in any operational system and
infrastructure as code system you
want to have automation that does
positive things you also want to have
automation that stops before it does
harmful or destructive things both are
important agreed how do you achieve
resiliency and fault tolerance in a bare
metal setup
it can be really challenging to have
resilience some of the protocols that we
depend on like dhcp
tftp boot
you know out-of-band management aren't
necessarily designed with resilience in
mind
and so
what we've ended up doing
is actually building h a components for
dhcp infrastructure and then being able
to reset and restart these processes
some of the protocols that are being
used are very hard to change they've
been around for a long time and they
didn't think through a lot of the
resilience aspects when they were just
worried about how do you pixie boot a
server as a matter of fact
pixie booting and server especially
incredibly limited from a software
capability so
it really requires you thinking through
externally how do you encourage that
system to be
built in a really sustainable way one of
the things i can say that we we do that
you might not think of out of the box as
ha resiliency but has proven to be the
simplest over time
is our infrastructure's code systems are
all very set up as an immutable artifact
set so part of what we do to make things
very resilient is we make it incredibly
easy to recreate your environment and
have all the artifacts that went into
building that environment version
controlled and then bundled together in
a very packaged way and so
while it's important to be able to come
back and say oh i have my infrastructure
and my boot provision system is offline
i'm stuck that's that's a big problem
you can and we support building a
multi-node ha cluster and having a
consensus algorithm that will keep it
all up that's great in some cases it's
really nice to just be able to say yeah
something happened i'm going to rebuild
that system from scratch and everything
will be just fine take a backup have
backups going of of the infrastructure
and be able to recover
sometimes that's actually the simplest
and best component for this algorithm it
is worth noting
a lot of what our customers have been
able to do and what we advocate is being
much more dynamic in how you manage
these environments so
the wrong answer for being more
resilient is to
turn off the automation and provisioning
systems and just pretend like your
servers never need to be reprovisioned
or reconfigured that is the absolute
wrong way to go about building
resilience in your system it's much
better to go in and say you know what i
want my bare metal infrastructure to be
very dynamic and be updated every month
and rebooted and patched and reviewed
we found that the most resilient systems
here are the ones where their bare metal
infrastructure is actually the most
dynamic and they are constantly
reprovisioning and repaving and
resetting the systems and patching the
bios and keeping things up to date that
the more dynamic and the more turnover
they have in that system from an
operation system and rebuilding and
resetting all that
those actually create much more
resilient data centers as a whole
it does put more stress on the
provisioning infrastructure
around that but the overall system is
much much stronger as a consequence
i can see some infrastructure as code
and some agile principles being applied
over here where one of the principles in
agile is the more often you release the
more resilient your system is and you're
pretty much
doing something similar over here
that's exactly right we're calling that
process infrastructure pipelines some
people would call it a continuous
infrastructure pipeline
and the idea here is when you're dealing
with bare metal systems
we've talked about this a couple of
times already and it's worth reinforcing
the thing that makes bare metal
challenging is i don't have one api that
does all the work i actually have to
walk through a series of steps
especially if you then look at building
the app the operating system and
installing platforms on top of the
operating system and then get bringing
those into clusters
that's an integrated workflow that has
to operate end to end so very much like
we've seen ci cd pipelines
really really help development processes
from an agile perspective where you can
make those incremental changes and then
that change is going to automatically
flow all the way through into production
delivery
if you do that at the bare metal layer
or even at the virtualized
infrastructure layer you have dramatic
results from being able to make small
quick changes and then watch those get
implemented
very quickly through the system so
you're exactly right that's agile
mindset
of small quick
constantly testing refining
executing that process
translates into really really dynamic
much more resilient infrastructure as a
whole
we will now move to the next section
which is about standards and tool set
but i do want to continue the
conversation about the infrastructure
pipeline
so on the infrastructure pipeline how is
there tooling is it
mature and do you have a
mature tool set similar to what we have
called for the cicd pipelines
what rackn builds our product is called
digital rebar and that has been in use
running data centers that have thousands
of servers and tens and hundreds of
sites global footprints and so we're
very comfortable with that process and
being able to bring in
components in that process it is
something that more generally we've seen
companies trying to build themselves
with either a lot of bash scripts right
they're sort of trying to cobble
together pieces and i'll talk about the
pieces in a second or they're sort of
trying to stuff it at the end of a ci cd
pipeline where they'll call out to a
terraform script or an ansible script
and they'll try and run those things
together
that's a starting point the challenge is
that it really is doesn't become a
operational platform it's important to
when you're dealing with infrastructure
to really have
visibility and insight into the
processes as the running and it's also
really important that the process is run
from a data center you don't want to run
infrastructure pipelines from a desktop
system because they have to be available
all the time the state of them has to be
available back into those systems we do
see
a lot of excitement around some really
good tools that we leverage too in in
building our pipelines things like
terraform or pollumi that are
infrastructure's code tools that
interface to sort of wrap the cloud apis
and provide a slightly more consistent
experience for
programmatically interfacing to a cloud
in a generic way we can talk about more
generally how those aren't as consistent
as we would like the goal of an
infrastructure pipeline is that it
doesn't really care what infrastructure
you're running underneath it should be
an abstraction
and then we see a lot of configuration
which is a very different operation
where you're actually working inside of
the system inside of the operating
system and installing software and
configuring firewalls and adding user
accounts and things like that typically
people use something like ansible shaft
puppet salt for that
those types of processes are also
important to have in the pipeline and
should be connected together so that you
can go straight from provisioning
into configuration and then run that as
a seamless process
i was going to ask you about terraform
and whether that's applicable for bare
metal but you've already answered my
question
terraform and bare metal is an
interesting chunk terraform really is a
driver for other apis it doesn't do
anything by itself it's it's a you know
an api it's a front end for apis
and then it stores some state and the
way it stores state can be a challenge
from a pipeline perspective and i'm
happy to dig deeper into that
but
you can use tariff i mean one of the
things that we've done is taken our api
for bare metal as a service and wrapped
it in terraform so you can use a
terraform provider to do that work
what we found though was that people
really wanted the end-to-end pipeline
pieces and so
if you're building a pipeline and
terraform is providing say provisioning
in that pipeline like we use it for
cloud interfacing if you have a way to
do it that doesn't require you to call
into terraform it's not as important
from that process and from an
infrastructure as code perspective we've
really stepped
above the terraform aspect and asked how
do people want to build data center
infrastructure how do they want to build
clusters how do they want to do the
configuration after the systems are
provisioned and how they want to do the
controls
leading into the decision to build a
cluster
those operations are actually really the
conversations that we have more from an
infrastructure as code perspective not
the how do i turn on vms in another
system
does bare metal have an api what is the
api of the server itself
the servers have traditionally they've
had something called ipmi so the
variance in this is very very large
most enterprise class servers have
out-of-band management or bmc
is another acronym that people use for
that the vendors have their own
brand names for it for dell it's drac
for hp it's ilo
a whole bunch of acronyms behind all
those those those names but
fundamentally those use proprietary
protocols the legacy ones use something
called ipmi which is an ip based
management interface so it's a network
based access to turn the machine on or
off ipmi is there's some basics that
work sort of everywhere but once you get
past the basics every server is
different and then there's a new
standard coming around slowly called
redfish that has
a little bit more consistency than ipmi
but vendors still have their own
overlays and implementations of it and
so it's handy to have some convergence
on apis but the servers themselves are
different and so
it can be very hard to automate against
it
and then you have a whole ban like all
the edge servers have their own
you know they might not have any out of
band management interface and so you're
stuck only to being able to pixie boot
it some servers use another protocol
that sort of rides on top of their main
networking
that you can sort of use to do power
controls and things like that it's
unfortunately all over the map from that
perspective and
can be very hard to automate
because you have to know how to reach
the server you have to be in the network
that has the out-of-band management on
it you have to have the credentials
hopefully please please please everybody
if you're listening to this make sure
that you set passwords ideally unique
per server passwords on
all of your out-of-band management
interfaces
if you're attaching those to the
internet and you're not changing the
passwords you are exposing your server
to the internet and it will be
hacked and taken down those are very
easy ingress points for people these are
challenges and that's what customers
that we work with are very careful about
those interfaces and how they're exposed
and not leaving them at the faults or
not you know making sure they have
certificates and a whole bunch of
security that goes into improving those
apis because they are
incredibly powerful when it comes to
owning and managing a server
our listeners might like you to explain
what do you mean by out of band
so when you take a piece of bare metal
really any system because virtual
machines have the same concept and it's
worth understanding
how the controls work but if i take a
regular server i install an operating
system on it and i start using that
server the normal way to configure that
server is what we would call in-band
where i talk to a network interface on
the server usually through like ssh or
through its web port
and then i log into the server and i
start doing things with the server and i
can even do reboots and things like that
we call that a soft reboot where you're
asking the operating system to restart
that would be in-band control our
software most software has an agent that
you can run on the system and if you
need to make changes to the system you
can ask that agent to do that work for
you and that would be in-band control
it's the primary way that most systems
are managed and it's it's a really good
secure way to do it but
sometimes that doesn't work if your
operating system crashed or the
operating system isn't installed yet or
you might not have the access
credentials to that system you need
another way to get access to it
and that's what out of band management
is so in out-of-band management there is
a
back door it's it's not exactly like an
operating system backdoor it's it's a
network access
that talks to the motherboard of the
server as a separate service it's a
monitoring system
management system and through that you
can
control the server you can stop and
restart it you can
update the bios change the configuration
settings you can literally do all of the
setting actions on the systems
and it's important to understand these
control mechanisms are actually the way
you configure the server predominantly
there's no buttons dot knobs or dials on
the server the server usually has a on
off button
and that's about it if you want to
modify a server you're either using the
out-of-band management port
or you're rebooting it pushing f2 to get
into the bios configuration and using a
keyboard and mouse or mostly a keyboard
to set whatever you want on those on the
settings that's the difference from an
out-of-band management it's worth noting
if you're dealing with a vm and you're
talking to the hypervisor control plane
that's effectively out-of-band
management too so if i've installed say
vmware and i'm talking to vmware that is
an out-of-band management for a vm if i
was talking to a cloud and talking to
the cloud apis that's out-of-band
management for the cloud instance thank
you i'd also like you to
touch on devops automation how does
devops automation work with bare metal
yeah devops automation from our
perspective is really very much the same
thing is what i would consider
infrastructure is code automation
and it's this idea that i'm building
processes to control the system with
bare metal it's really the same once you
have that machine bootstrapped and
installed
and you know we have an api that lets
you do that so your devops tooling can
talk to
your bare metal apis
or your cloud apis you know provision a
system that's the provisioning part of
the devops automation
usually terraform pollutants something
like that and then the configuration
side of it so devops tooling would be
chef puppet ansible salt
your favorite bash scripts or powershell
scripts actually running in band on the
system would be you know a lot of people
think of devops automation as sort of
that part of the process where you're
actually on the system installing
software
configuring it making all those pieces
go
but it's really a continuum i i would
fall back when i talk about devops to
the idea of the devops processes more
where people are looking at getting
teams to communicate together and then
building that pipeline and that
automation sometimes when we get very
tied into like oh my devops tools you
know ansible is my devops automation
tool you're really only looking at one
piece of how that works it's super
important to have automation tools that
do the work you need to do you certainly
don't want to log in and do anything by
hand you just also need to understand
that the individual
parts of your pipeline those are
important tools they need to work well
and then you have to take a step back
and figure out how to connect them
together so
the devops tooling when people look at
that every devops automation component i
have i should have something that calls
it and it's something that it calls that
that's what makes a pipeline
in this last section i'd like to close
off the show talking about what's in the
future
what are some of the exciting new ideas
and innovations in the infrastructure
space that you would like our listeners
to know about
infrastructure is really exciting
there's a lot going on
that people
haven't been paying attention to because
we've been so wrapped up in cloud
so i like the opportunity to sort of
have people step back and say wow what
what is going on in the infrastructure
space
because there's a lot of innovation here
one of the things that we're seeing and
you can access it in cloud
infrastructure too is more and more arm
processors so
intel and amd processor styles have
really dominated the market for the last
20 years
cell phones and other tech like that
have been using arm processors but in a
very captive way we're starting to see
arm become available for
data center use and enterprise use and
so i see that from a power management
perspective from a price performance
perspective and also from an edge
utility perspective we're going to see a
lot more servers using arm architecture
chips it's going to require
dual compiling and there's some there's
some challenges around it but i think
that the footprint of that architecture
is going to be very powerful for people
especially as we we've gotten better at
bare metal management you could have 10
arm servers
and manage those for less than it would
cost you to put 10 comparable virtual
machines on a amd intel class machine
so incredibly powerful stories for that
the other thing that we're tracking is
interesting is something called a
smartnic sometimes these are called
supervisory controllers or ipu's where
they're basically a whole separate
computer often with an arm chip in it
that runs inside of your primary server
and that second computer can then
override the networking the storage i
can actually run services like the
hypervisor for the the server that
you're you're talking to and so that
it's basically the supervisory system
it's its own life cycle its own controls
but then it is able to provide
security
monitor the traffic going in and out i
can offload some of the compute
processing like by running the
hypervisor so that you can amazon does
this with all of their their servers you
can actually put the server that's
running the virtual machines only runs
virtual machines and the the
coordination and control of those
virtual machines is all done on this
smart neck and it's been offloaded for
those control systems
the capability of having that type of
supervisory control in a system
really changes how we would look at a
server it might mean that you get more
performance out of it it might mean that
you can create a layer of security in
those systems that is is really
important it might mean that you can
bridge in
virtual
devices so you might be able to
create a server and we have partners
that are doing exactly this that you can
create a server that has you know 100
gpu instances in it instead of just one
or two or maybe eight but you can
actually change the physical
characteristics of a server in a dynamic
way
and so it really changes the way we
think about
how servers get built that's something
that's called converged infrastructure
or composable infrastructure is another
term in it and so we're seeing those
types of operations
really
change how we're defining the systems
the other thing that those two lead to
is a real growth in edge computing and
edge infrastructure
and in those cases we're getting out of
traditional data centers and we're
putting
computational power
into the environment people talk about
like smart farms or factories or wind
farms or real popular examples or smart
cities where every intersection could
have a little data center at it that
manages the traffic for flowing through
that intersection people are getting
excited about augmented reality or
virtual reality which is going to
require you to have
very low latency processing close into
where you are
and those environments all would be
prime locations where you would say i
need more processing power
closer to where i am i'm going to
distribute my data center
so that it's local and that change where
we have to be able to manage
and run that infrastructure and power
that infrastructure and secure that
infrastructure actually has the
potential to really rewrite
how data centers are thought of today
where we're used to big buildings with
big cooling and rows and rows of servers
and and you know people with crash carts
running around to manage them
we could be moving i think we have to be
moving into a world where while we have
that
we also have a lot more
5 10 20 machine data centers power you
know maybe powered by very low low power
arm systems or
secured in a municipal location or you
know walmart had been talked about like
every walmart could be a data center
that runs the whole shopping center
around it
we're moving into a place where we
really can decentralize how computation
is run and part of these other
innovations i talked about are key to
helping build
that coming and so we're seeing
infrastructure infrastructure management
and then infrastructure is code
techniques to then manage all of that
infrastructure as the future really
exciting new ways to think about how
we're building all these things together
sounds super exciting so just to
summarize you touched on arm processors
smart neck
ipu's converged infrastructure and edge
what does ipu stand for ipu stands for
the infrastructure processing unit some
people are calling these things dpus
there's all sorts of names for
these different processing units that
we're adding on to the primary interface
in part because the word smartnic is
very limiting it sounds like it's only a
network interface but the ipu is
designed to look at it more as a storage
and security and a hypervisor control
system i don't think the final name on
this is set i think that we're going to
continue to have different
vendors trying to come up with their own
branded marketing around what this is
going to be so it's important that
people
sort of scratch behind the surface what
does that actually mean is that like
something else and think through what
they are fundamentally
it's this idea that i have a supervisory
computer
monitoring and being the maybe the
storage interface or the bus interface
for
what we've traditionally called the main
computer and it'll also take over what
we spent a lot of time talking about our
out-of-band management our baseboard
management controllers which is bmc's
those are usually not considered
smartnics or ipu's they're just
not wired into the systems enough
they're just for power management and
patching
obviously bare metal infrastructure as a
service is a very powerful offering with
an evolving ecosystem
but if there was one thing a software
engineer should remember from our show
what would it be
when
software engineers are approaching
automation
a lot of the automation tools have been
designed with very narrow focus to
accomplish
sort of a very narrow scope of work
and i think that
we need software engineers to think like
software engineers
in
ops devops and automation contexts and
really encourage
software engineering practice so reuse
modularity pipelining where they have
dev test and prod cycles
git commits and source code controls
that thinking
is essential in building really
resilient automation and it's been
missing
i've been in the op space for decades
now and we haven't had the apis or the
or the tools
until recently to really start
thinking about
the software engineering process for
automation
and really bringing that to bear and
it's time and so what i would hope is
that a software engineer listening to
this and getting involved in site
reliability engineering or automation
doesn't uh give up there and just start
crafting bespoke scripts or one-off
modules but actually goes and looks for
ways that they can
take more of a platform approach to the
automation and create these repeatable
processes and infrastructure pipelines
that
we've proven have incredible roi for
customers when they get out of the
do it in a way that only works for me
and one-off scripts and very narrowly
defined automation layers
so i would hope that they look at it as
a software engineering problem and a
systems problem instead
was there anything i missed that you'd
like to mention
this has been a really thorough
interview we have covered bare metal
pieces we've covered
infrastructures code i do think there's
one thing that's worth pointing out
these different types of infrastructures
are really not that different
and so i like that we've come in and
explored the differences
between
all these systems
at the end of the day they're still
composed of very similar parts and we
should be able to have much more unified
processes
where we look at infrastructure much
more generically
and so i do think it's important
to sort of reflect back on all of this
variation and say okay wait a second i
can actually create more uniform
processes and see that happening and
it's worth noting a lot of these things
that we went into very deep detail on
and the details are important
in some ways it's like knowing how the
cpu works you can use infrastructure
without having to worry about some of
these nuances it's useful information to
have because when systems are operating
you you understand it better but at the
end of the day you can
work at a higher level of abstraction
and then keep going and i would
encourage people to remember that they
have the choice to dig into the details
and they should
and also they can enjoy abstractions
that make a lot of that complexity go
away
people can follow you on twitter but how
else can people get in touch twitter i
am vehicle on twitter and and i'm very
active there that is a great way to to
do it they are welcome to reach out to
me through rackn and visit rakkon's
website to do that you know contact me
via linkedin those are the primary
places that i am active and i do love a
good conversation and q a on twitter so
i would highly highly suggest that one
is if you want to reach me that's the
easiest way
we will link to your twitter handle in
the show notes rob thank you for coming
on the show it's been a real pleasure
this is brijesh ahmad for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thank you
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening